Guide to the Tyre Glen papers, 1806-1874 and undated RL.10035
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Tyre Glen papers
1806-1882 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Glen, Tyre
RL.10035
4 Linear Feet
Tyre Glen was a slave trader, planter, postmaster, and merchant in North Carolina. This collection consists largely of business papers, particularly of financial and legal documents concerning the slave trade in North Carolina, Virginia and Alabama as well as possibly other locations. In addition to copious information on slave trading in the 1830s and 1840s, the collection includes references to Glen's Union sympathies and claims for horses confiscated by the U.S. Army; farming; exemptions from the Confederate Army and other topics.
Biographical note
Tyre Glen began trading in slaves in the early 1820s; he purchased slaves in Surry County, North Carolina and neighboring counties as well as in Virginia. In 1846, Glen became postmaster at Red Plains, Yadkin County, North Carolina. He was also an active farmer and sometime speculator who was a subscriber in the Yadkin Navigation Company.
Glen petitioned for exemption from military service in the Confederate Army on the plea that he furnished the government with mules and supplies. After the war Glen retailed liquor at Salisbury in Rowan County, along with other businesses. he also continued his farming operation until his death in 1875.
Collection Overview
This collection consists largely of business papers, particularly of financial and legal documents concerning the slave trade in North Carolina, Virginia and Alabama as well as possibly other locations. In addition to copious information on slave trading in the 1830s and 1840s, the collection includes references to Glen's Union sympathies and claims for horses confiscated by the U.S. Army; farming; exemptions from the Confederate Army and other topics.
Volumes include accounts of slaves, mercantile interests, and general expenses. Also included in the collection are two volumes concerning a firm known as Poindexter and Palmer operating a general store in North Carolina. These records contain numerous accounts of individuals from the region included H.P. Poindexter, various members of the Clingman family and Richard C. Puryear.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Tyre Glen papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a acquired in 1939 and 1993.
Existence and Location of Copies
This collection has been microfilmed as part of Records of Antebellum Southern Plantations from the Revolution through the Civil War project, series F, part 3.
Slave trade -- United States; General stores -- North Carolina -- Yadkin County; Slave traders -- Records; Account books; Slave traders -- North Carolina; Daybooks; Glen, Tyre
- Tyre Glen papers, 1806-1882 and undated; 1
  - Introductory Materials, tgp150419
  - Correspondence, 1806-1829; tgp150422 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1830; tgp150483 (Box 1, Folder 2 - 2A)
  - Correspondence, 1831-1833; tgp150607 (Box 1, Folder 3 - 3A)
  - Correspondence, 1834-1835; tgp150780 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1836-1839; tgp150854 (Box 1, Folder 5 - 5A)
  - Correspondence, 1840-1845; tgp160001 (Box 1, Folder 6 - 6A)
  - Correspondence, 1846; tgp160132 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1847-1849; tgp160183 (Box 2, Folder 1 - 1A)
  - Correspondence, 1850-1855; tgp160389 (Box 2, Folder 2 - 2A)
  - Correspondence, 1856-1859; tgp160582 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1859; tgp160678 (Box 2, Folder 4 - 4A)
  - Correspondence, 1860-1869; tgp160883 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1870-1882; tgp170001 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, undated; tgp170113 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Account Book, 1830-1833; tgp170146 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Account Book, 1834-1853; tgp170172 (Box 2, Folder 8A)
  - Poindexter and Palmer Daybook, 1841-1843; tgp170222 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Poindexter and Palmer Inventory, 1843; tgp170445 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Account Book, 1836-1859; tgp170465 (Volume M:1420)
  - Ledger, 1841-1844; tgp170445 (Volume F:1421)
  - Account book, 1838-1840 (Box Acc 93/195, 1)
  - Daybook, 1856-1874 (Box Acc 93/195, 1)